<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Exodus, or, The decease of holy men and ministers consider'd in the nature, certainty, causes, and improvement thereof : a sermon preach't Sept. 12. 1675 : by occasion of the much lamented death of that learned and reverend minister of Christ, Dr. Lazarus Seaman ...</title>
            <author>Jenkyn, William, 1613-1685.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 32 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A46806</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing J638</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18544</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12396085</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12396085</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61171</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A46806)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61171)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 920:8)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Exodus, or, The decease of holy men and ministers consider'd in the nature, certainty, causes, and improvement thereof : a sermon preach't Sept. 12. 1675 : by occasion of the much lamented death of that learned and reverend minister of Christ, Dr. Lazarus Seaman ...</title>
                  <author>Jenkyn, William, 1613-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>62 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edward Brewster and William Cooper ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bristol Public Library, Bristol, England.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 62.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Seaman, Lazarus, d. 1675.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61171:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>EXODUS: OR, The DECEASE of Holy Men and MINISTERS, Conſider'd in The Nature, Certainty, Cauſes, and Improvement thereof.</p>
            <p>A SERMON Preach't <hi>Sept.</hi> 12. 1675.</p>
            <p>By occaſion of the much lamented Death of that Learned and Reverend Miniſter of Chriſt, Dr. <hi>LAZAR<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S SEAMAN,</hi> Late Paſtor of <hi>Alhallows-Bread-ſtreet, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>WILLIAM JENKYN,</hi> late Miniſter of the Goſpel at <hi>Chriſt-Church, London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON: Printed for <hi>Edward Brewſter</hi> and <hi>William Cooper,</hi> at the <hi>Crane</hi> in St. <hi>Pauls</hi>-Church-Yard, and at the <hi>Pellican</hi> in <hi>Little-Brittain.</hi> 1675.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:61171:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61171:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>EXOD<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S:</hi> OR, <hi>The</hi> Deceaſe <hi>of Holy Men and Miniſters conſidered,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THat <hi>ſingle</hi> diſſuaſive from this my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, the Inſufficiency (I mean) of my <hi>dwarfiſh</hi> endeavours to reach the <hi>height</hi> of Doctor <hi>Seamans</hi> Worth, and ſo to add any honour to his venerable memory, was eaſily overcome by a <hi>double</hi> inducement to this preſent Performance; Firſt, the <hi>dying deſire</hi> (to me the <hi>command</hi>) of my dear and deceaſed Friend: Next, the <hi>importunity</hi> of his afflicted and affectionate Flock, for my per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming of this laſt reſpect, which ſo deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly I owe to their late Learned and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Paſtor. If the Angels lately carried him (as they carried <hi>Lazarus</hi>) from all his
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61171:3"/>
               <hi>ſores</hi> and <hi>ſorrows,</hi> into the <hi>boſom</hi> of a <hi>ſweet and quiet repoſe,</hi> how can you or I deny a ſhort endeavour ſeverally to bear our parts in bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up his memory, who had not only the <hi>attendance</hi> of <hi>Angels</hi> when he dyed, but the <hi>title</hi> of an <hi>Angel</hi> while he lived, conjoin'd with thoſe (not <hi>titular,</hi> but) <hi>real,</hi> yea <hi>raiſed</hi> endowments, which the tongue of an <hi>Angel</hi> is much fitter than mine to ſet forth in their due and genuine perfection. But as I never did, ſo now I much leſs do delight in <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face</hi> or <hi>Apology,</hi> perceiving that probably I may thereby raiſe your ſorrow to that exceſs, which may hinder your attendance upon a more <hi>uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Subject,</hi> which you may find preſented to you in the
<q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>2<hi rend="sup">d</hi>
                     </hi> Epiſtle of Peter, <hi>ch. 1. ver. 15. in theſe words,</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Moreover I will endeavour, that you may be able <hi>after my deceaſe,</hi> to have theſe things always in remembrance.</p>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>DIvine <hi>Exhortations</hi> and holy <hi>Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> propounded to us, are in <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ.</hi> 12.11, ſaid to be as <hi>Nails;</hi> but ſuch is the hardneſs of our hearts, that as Nails
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61171:3"/>for their more eaſie entrance and piercing, are often dipt in oyl, and after always driven with many knocks, and ſtrokes, and blows; ſo <hi>holy Exhortations</hi> muſt be dipt in the ſweetning and ſuppl'ing love of the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horter,</hi> and ſet home beſides by ſtrong and forcible reaſons and arguments, to make them prevalent and penetrative. This bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> giving to thoſe Chriſtians to whom he wrote that great <hi>Exhortation</hi> of progreſſive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and proficiency in holineſs, plainly obſerv'd this way of <hi>Exhortation;</hi> Firſt, he dips the <hi>Nail</hi> of <hi>Exhortation</hi> in the <hi>oyl</hi> of <hi>love</hi> and <hi>ſweetneſs,</hi> v. 12. Telling thoſe Chriſtians to whom he wrote, that he granted they were knowing perſons, and that they were <hi>eſtabliſhed in the preſent Truth;</hi> he yields that they were already both <hi>informati &amp; confirmati,</hi> as <hi>Gerard</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>informed</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed</hi> in the truth; acknowledging what they had, that ſo they may the better admit what they needed; hereby he yet inſinuates, that though they knew the truth, yet their memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries needed refreſhment; though they were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſh'd, yet by reaſon of their inward cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions and outward temptations, they might want further Confirmation. In a word, the Apoſtle to win acceptance to this <hi>Exhortation,</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:61171:4"/>tells them in effect, That he doth not lay the firſt Colours, but only refreſhes and waſhes them over again. Secondly, As the Apoſtle dips the <hi>Nail</hi> in the <hi>oil of love,</hi> ſo he ſtrikes it home with the <hi>blows of forcible arguments and perſwaſions;</hi> and the firſt argument is laid down in <hi>ver.</hi> 12, in the word <hi>[wherefore] Wherefore,</hi> ſays he, <hi>I will put you in remembrance.</hi> But wherefore was that <hi>wherefore</hi> put down? The force of it lies thus, Becauſe by your progreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiveneſs in Grace, proficiency in Holineſs, there will be a more <hi>abundant Entrance</hi> made for you into the Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Chriſt: As if he had ſaid, If you have but a <hi>little</hi> grace, though you may get into Heaven, yet it will be more <hi>difficultly</hi> and <hi>creepingly;</hi> but if you go with a full meaſure of Grace, with proficiency in Holineſs, by adding one degree of grace unto another; then there ſhall be an <hi>abundant entrance</hi> made for you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Kingdom of Chriſt. As when a <hi>mean</hi> and <hi>ordinary</hi> perſon comes to your Houſes, 'tis enough to open the <hi>Common-wicket,</hi> or the <hi>leſſer-door</hi> for his admiſſion: but if there come ſome <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>great Perſon</hi> to viſit you, then you ſet open the <hi>great Gates</hi> for his Entrance; then you make an <hi>abundant Entrance</hi> for him. So
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61171:4"/>here, if you will be great in Grace, eminent in Holineſs, high proficients in Obedience, then there ſhall be <hi>abundant entrance</hi> made for you into the everlaſting Kingdom of our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus; Then ſays the Apoſtle, you ſhall go into Heaven with more aſſurance of the Love of God, with the more confidence and courage; then you ſhall go even with joy, unto Eternal Joy.</p>
            <p>The ſecond Motive is the <hi>meetneſs and fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> of him to give them this <hi>Exhortation</hi> to progreſſiveneſs and proficiency in Holineſs, and that is in <hi>ver.</hi> 13, <hi>I judged it meet,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, in regard of my Office, of my Place, being a <hi>Miniſter,</hi> an <hi>Apoſtle.</hi> It was not enough for this bleſſed man to have the title of an <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> unleſs he did by a correſpondent-carriage anſwer that Title by endeavouring the welfare of his people.</p>
            <p>The third argument is taken from the <hi>op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity</hi> that ſtill he had to exhort them, laid down <hi>ver.</hi> 13, <hi>I am yet,</hi> ſays he, in the body, <hi>in my tabernacle;</hi> I have not yet put it off, and therefore I muſt take my preſent opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and becauſe yet I have time, I will make <hi>uſe</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, The next argument to quicken them to proficiency in Holineſs, is, from the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61171:5"/>
               <hi>nearneſs of his Death,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, laying off <hi>of my tabernacle is near,</hi> q. d. therefore I will bleſs you before I die; the leſs our time, the faſter muſt be our working: <hi>ſhort ſeaſons</hi> require <hi>quick ſervices:</hi> the ſmaller quantity of paper we have to write in, the cloſer muſt be our writing. And the Apoſtle confirms the nearneſs of his death from the declaration of Chriſt himſelf, that you have in <hi>John</hi> 21.18, <hi>When thou ſhalt be old,</hi> ſays Chriſt, <hi>another ſhall gird thee;</hi> meaning, he ſhould die a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent death by Crucifixion; and becauſe Chriſt ſhew'd him that this ſhould be when <hi>he was old, Peter</hi> finding himſelf now in years, could not but judg this prediction would ſhortly be fulfilled.</p>
            <p>The fifth and laſt argument is in the words of my Text laid down in <hi>ver.</hi> 15, <hi>More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, I will endeavour that after my deceaſe you may have theſe things always in remembrance;</hi> and the argument intended in theſe words to ſet home the <hi>Exhortation,</hi> is his deſire to bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit their Souls <hi>after his death; After my deceaſe.</hi> In the whole Verſe we may moſt clearly take notice of theſe two parts:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Apoſtles <hi>diligence, I will endeavour</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I will endeavour with all my might,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61171:5"/>with all my Solicitude, with all readineſs and forwardneſs, with the utmoſtneſs of my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours I will put forth my ſelf, that you may think of the Truths in which I now inſtruct you after my <hi>deceaſe.</hi> That's the firſt part of the Text, his <hi>Diligence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly, There's contained in theſe words the Apoſtles <hi>deſign,</hi> which was, that they might <hi>have theſe things always in remembrance,</hi> even <hi>after his Deceaſe.</hi> In which I note principally theſe two things: The firſt is that <hi>Duty</hi> he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns to put them <hi>upon,</hi> viz. <hi>the having theſe things always in remembrance:</hi> (My diſcourſe upon which words I intend ſhall be the work of the Afternoon).</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, The <hi>time</hi> when he did deſire to have theſe things in their Remembrance, and that was <hi>after his Deceaſe.</hi> Theſe words then <hi>after my Deceaſe,</hi> I ſhall only by Gods aſſiſtance at this time inſiſt upon, and I ſhall handle them under a threefold Conſideration.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As giving us an apt and ſuitable Title of the death of the Saints, it is called <hi>a Deceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly, As diſcovering the <hi>lot</hi> of <hi>Peter,</hi> a great and famous Servant of Chriſt, and a bleſſed A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, even he among the reſt of the faithful was likewiſe to have his <hi>Deceaſe, my Deceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:61171:6"/>
            <p n="3">3dly, As intending the <hi>time</hi> and <hi>ſeaſon</hi> of his deſires to benefit the Souls of theſe Chriſtians, that was <hi>after</hi> his deceaſe: 1. <hi>Deceaſe,</hi> 2. <hi>My</hi> deceaſe, 3. <hi>After</hi> my deceaſe.</p>
            <p>I ſhall ſpeak of theſe three particulars (God willing) in their order: And</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the firſt of theſe, the <hi>apt and fit</hi> Title of Death, it is called here a <hi>Deceaſe,</hi> in the <hi>Greek</hi> it is
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which ſignifies properly <hi>a departure or going away;</hi> and it is obſervable, that when Chriſt was upon the Mount of Transfiguration, and that <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> ſpake concerning his <hi>deceaſe,</hi> Luke 9.31, the ſame word
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is there uſed; and that <hi>Peter</hi> was then in the Mount with Jeſus, who here alſo calls his death his
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or his <hi>deceaſe:</hi> And in both places there is a clear alluſion to that <hi>Exodus</hi> or <hi>departure of</hi> the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of the land <hi>of Egypt</hi> towards <hi>Canaan,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard whereof the ſecond book of <hi>Moſes</hi> is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Exodus;</hi> the former part of the book of <hi>Exodus,</hi> containing a full deſcription of the manner and means of the departure of the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt.</hi> And <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.22, when <hi>Joſeph</hi> made mention of the departing of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt;</hi> in the <hi>Greek</hi> it is, <hi>Joſeph</hi> made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:61171:6"/>of the
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of the <hi>going away,</hi> or <hi>departing</hi> of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> ſo that this <hi>Exodus</hi> or <hi>deceaſe</hi> in the Text, is a clear alluſion to that
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that <hi>departure</hi> of the people of God out of <hi>Egypt</hi> to the Land of <hi>Canaan.</hi> Nor is this my opinion alone, for <hi>Grotius</hi> upon my Text expreſſeth himſelf fully for it in theſe words, <hi>hic exitus figuratus per illum ex Aegypto:</hi> This <hi>departure</hi> here mentioned by <hi>Peter</hi> was figured by that <hi>Exodus</hi> or <hi>departure</hi> out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> and <hi>Brugenſis</hi> tells us upon the words, <hi>Luke</hi> 9.31, where it is ſaid that they ſpake of Chriſts
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>departure,</hi> That there is an alluſion to the
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> when <hi>Moſes</hi> led them out of <hi>Egypt;</hi> ſo likewiſe <hi>Cyril,</hi> and others. And <hi>Gerard</hi> upon the Text tells us, the Antients were wont to call death an <hi>Exodus,</hi> a departing out of the body to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Countrey, the Heavenly <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt Obſervation then is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is a lively reſemblance and ſimilitude between the Exodus, or departure, of the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of</hi> Iſrael <hi>out of</hi> Egypt, <hi>and the Exodus, or departure, of a Saint out of this Life.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the proſecution of this Meditation I ſhall, 1, Explain it. 2dly, I ſhall give you a brief application of it, it being not that which I
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61171:7"/>deſign to inſiſt upon. There are theſe three ſuitable reſemblances between a Saints <hi>Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> or departure when dying, and the <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raelites Exodus</hi> or departure out of <hi>Egypt:</hi> 1. Conſidering from <hi>whence</hi> the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> went when they went from <hi>Egypt</hi> into <hi>Cana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> 2dly, Conſidering what <hi>way</hi> they went. 3dly, Conſidering to what <hi>Countrey</hi> or place they went.</p>
            <p n="1">1. From <hi>whence</hi> the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted when they went: Take it in three par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars: 1. It was a <hi>ſtrange</hi> Land from which they went, <hi>terra aliena;</hi> ſo a ſtrange Land is called, <hi>Exod.</hi> 2.22.
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and <hi>Egypt</hi> is called, <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.13.
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a Land not their own. <hi>Iſraelites</hi> are oft ſaid to be <hi>ſtrangers</hi> in the Land of Egypt, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.21, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19.34. <hi>Deut.</hi> 10.19. and in alluſion to this it is thought, that the people of God are ſo fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in Scripture called <hi>ſtrangers,</hi> Heb. 11.13. <hi>They confeſſed themſelves to be Pilgrims and ſtrangers</hi> upon the Earth. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 119.19, <hi>I am a ſtranger upon earth.</hi> 1 Chron. 29.15, <hi>We are ſtrangers and ſojourners, as were all our fathers. I beſeech you as Pilgrims and ſtrangers,</hi> 1 Pet. 2.11. <hi>Abſtain from fleſhly luſts that fight againſt the Soul.</hi> And the people of God that depart here
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:61171:7"/>out of the <hi>Egypt</hi> of this World, very fitly may be called <hi>ſtrangers upon earth,</hi> becauſe of their <hi>diſtance</hi> from their Relations: they are now abſent from their Father, their deareſt Friend; they ſee him <hi>not as he is;</hi> He oft-times hides his face from them in ſeeming diſpleaſure: they are far from their <hi>elder-brother</hi> the Lord Jeſus, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.23. They deſire <hi>to depart that they may be with him.</hi> While in the body we are <hi>abſent from the Lord,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.6. <hi>Him having not ſeen,</hi> 1 Pet. 1.8. And further, they are abſent from their <hi>Countrey,</hi> which is Heaven; that is <hi>patria juris,</hi> though the Earth <hi>be patria loci:</hi> the Earth is their Countrey here for <hi>place,</hi> but Heaven is the Countrey that they are deſigned for, that they of <hi>right be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long</hi> to, and long for; that they love to hear from, and towards which they daily walk. And they are <hi>ſtrangers,</hi> becauſe in their <hi>diſpoſitions, company, language, diet, apparel,</hi> (I mention all theſe in a <hi>ſpiritual</hi> ſenſe) they <hi>differ</hi> from the world. As to their <hi>diſpoſition,</hi> that's heavenly; they are born <hi>from above,</hi> they have a heavenly Principle; thoſe among whom they live are earthly in their inclinations, they <hi>ſavour</hi> and <hi>mind</hi> only <hi>earthly</hi> things. Saints love not the <hi>company</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:61171:8"/>of the wicked as wicked; they love it as Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicians, not as Companions; their <hi>delight</hi> is in thoſe that belong to their heavenly Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try. As to the <hi>Language</hi> they ſpeak, 'tis wholly heavenly, the Language of <hi>Canaan;</hi> and here they are in the midſt of a people of a <hi>ſtrange tongue.</hi> Their <hi>Dyet</hi> differs, the Earth is the worldlings food, he ſwallows it as in <hi>Job, Job</hi> 39.24, 'tis ſaid of the horſe, he <hi>ſwal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows</hi> the <hi>ground;</hi> but the godly feed and live upon the <hi>Word,</hi> and in that upon the fleſh and Blood of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> They differ in their <hi>Appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel,</hi> Saints <hi>put on the Lord Jeſus</hi> his righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs as <hi>imputed,</hi> and his grace and holineſs as <hi>imparted</hi> to them; but the wicked are clothed only with the defiled and defective rags of their own righteouſneſs, and the deformities of the old man, and corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. When the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> departed from <hi>Egypt,</hi> their <hi>Exodus,</hi> or departure, was <hi>e terra affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctionis,</hi> as 'tis call'd <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.52. from a <hi>trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome</hi> and afflicting Country; therefore Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture frequently ſpeaks concerning their <hi>afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> in <hi>Egypt, Exod.</hi> 3.7, their being <hi>bond-men</hi> in <hi>Egypt, Deut.</hi> 6.21, concerning the mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of their Infants in <hi>Egypt;</hi> concerning their
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61171:8"/>
               <hi>iron furnace in Egypt, Dent.</hi> 4.20. called an iron-furnace, becauſe much imployment of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> was ſpent in the melting and mollifying of iron, which doubtleſs was the ſoreſt and hotteſt work; and a little before they went away, their bricks were <hi>doubled,</hi> their burthens were increaſed; in one word, the <hi>Egyptian</hi> cruelties were extended to the very higheſt pitch of extremity. And when the people of God go out of the world, is not their <hi>Exodus,</hi> their departure, from an <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypt</hi> too in this regard? It is a troubleſome, hating, perſecuting world that they depart from. <hi>Mundus turbatur, &amp; amatur,</hi> the world is trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled and troubleſome (ſaith <hi>Auſtin</hi>), yet too much lov'd; and God makes the place of our diſtance from heaven an houſe of <hi>bondage</hi> and trouble, leſt we ſhould make it the place of our <hi>delight.</hi> 'Tis better for Gods <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that <hi>Egypt</hi> ſhould be a houſe of bondage than hoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitality; and God will have his people afflict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in it, that they may not be infected with it, and ſay, <hi>it is good for us to be here.</hi> When the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were coming into <hi>Egypt,</hi> how kindly did <hi>Pharaoh</hi> entertain them! how welcome were they to the <hi>Egyptians!</hi> but when they went out from thence, how were they
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61171:9"/>perſecuted! When the people of God are looking towards the world, and ſeeming to comply with it, then they ſhall be reſpected; but when they will leave it in their deport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practice, then they are hated. 'Tis good that <hi>Egyptians</hi> ſhould hate <hi>Iſrael,</hi> that they may not hurt them. When the world is moſt kind, 'tis moſt corrupting; and when it ſmiles moſt, it ſeduceth moſt. Were it not for the bondage of <hi>Egypt,</hi> we ſhould too much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the Idols and Onyons of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. When the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> departed out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> they departed <hi>e terra pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ana,</hi> out of a wicked idolatrous ſinful Country; therefore you ſo often read concerning the idols of the <hi>Egypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> the gods of the <hi>Egyptians, Jer.</hi> 43.12. <hi>Jer.</hi> 46.25. and particularly you have men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made, <hi>Joſh.</hi> 24.14, concerning the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> their ſerving the <hi>gods of the Egyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> which doubtleſs they did too frequently when they were amongſt them; ſo you read concerning the <hi>whoredoms of Egypt, Ezek.</hi> 23.8. And is not this as the world that we are leaving, the <hi>Egppt</hi> from which we are departing, when we are dying? The whole world, ſays the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, <hi>lies in wickedneſs,</hi> like a Swine in the midſt of the mire, wallowing and tumbling,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61171:9"/>immerſed in all kind of lewdneſs and profane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and it is called therefore, <hi>this preſent e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil World,</hi> Gal. 1.4. And the truth is, the people of God while here they abide, are too ready in this <hi>Egypt</hi> to learn the Language, and imitate the ſinful practiſes of <hi>Egypt.</hi> Water, though never ſo pure, running through a Brimſtony or Allomy Myne, will have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the ſavour, tang, and taſt of it; And the people of God, as frequently we ſee, and ſhould ſadly obſerve, although they are holy, purified and cleanſed, yet running through the Myne of a ſinful, profane World, have too great a tang and ſavour of its Impiety. I doubt not but the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> learned their Idolatry of worſhipping the golden Calf, of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> who worſhipped ſuch Idols. Thus you ſee <hi>from whence</hi> the <hi>Exodus,</hi> or departure, of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> was, it was from <hi>Egypt,</hi> that carries too great a reſemblance to the World, which the Saints leave when they die.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, What was the <hi>way</hi> of the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parting out of <hi>Egypt?</hi> It was through a <hi>red-Sea,</hi> a kind of <hi>living-death</hi> in appearance, or <hi>ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,</hi> wherein they expected every moment to be ſwallowed up, <hi>Pharaoh</hi> alſo purſuing of them. And the people of God muſt paſs to life ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61171:10"/>through a red-Sea of Perſecution and Bloud, as this great Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> did, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the prediction that he had from <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, Joh.</hi> 21.18; but always they muſt paſs to life through death: there is no going any other way; till the fetters of the body be knockt off, the Soul cannot get up to God. Death muſt be the threſhold of Life; we muſt be <hi>abſent from the body,</hi> before we can <hi>be preſent with the Lord.</hi> This is, as the way of ſins merit, ſo of Gods method. He writes death upon all things and perſons, before he enlivens and rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them. Nor is the paſſage of the Saints through the red-Sea of Death, without a pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> the Devil with his Army of Tentations, who will ever diſturb, where he cannot deſtroy; and purſue, though he cannot prevail; But bleſſed be Chriſt, who not only diſappoints, but deſtroys the deſtroyer.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, To what <hi>Countrey</hi> did they deſign to go when they departed out of <hi>Egypt?</hi> 'Twas to the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> thither they were tending and marching. And ſo likewiſe do the People of God, when they leave this <hi>Egypt,</hi> they go to a better Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> than that which is <hi>earthly,</hi> a Heavenly <hi>Countrey,</hi> an heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> though ſhadowed out, and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61171:10"/>typified by the <hi>earthly.</hi> I ſhall open it to you in three particulars.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was <hi>Terra Promiſſa,</hi> it was a <hi>Promiſed Land;</hi> therefore <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.15. it is there called the Land which God both promiſed and ſware to give the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> Their only Title to it was by Promiſe; God ow'd it to them no further than he had promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it to them: And the heavenly <hi>Canaan</hi> to which the dying Saints do go, is alſo a <hi>Land of Promiſe,</hi> 1 John 2.25. <hi>This is the promiſe that he hath promiſed, Eternal life.</hi> A Promiſe is a middle thing between Purpoſe and Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance: firſt there is the Purpoſe of God to ſave his People, his eternal Decree; then he promiſes it in the Goſpel, then performs it after Death; and ſo great is the Love of God to a true <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> an <hi>Iſraelite indeed,</hi> that he will not ſtay till the day of performance comes, but ſhews his Love in promiſing, before the time of performance. And hence you read of the <hi>promiſe of eternal Life,</hi> 2 Tim. 1.1. Heb. 9.15, the <hi>promiſe of the eternal Inheritance,</hi> and the Saints called <hi>the heirs of Promiſe;</hi> and hereby God both honours his own faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs in his peoples truſting him for Heaven, and tries his Saints ſincerity, who embrace
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:61171:11"/>Gods Promiſes before the Worlds Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances; and the Riches of the people of God on this ſide Heaven lies in this great Promiſe of Heaven. A Saint that hath a Promiſe of Heaven is richer than he is that hath all the Performances of the World.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, The Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> to which the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> went, was <hi>Terra Sancta,</hi> it was the <hi>Holy Land,</hi> and therefore it is called Gods <hi>holy habitation,</hi> Exod. 15.12; and <hi>Hieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> the beauty of the land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the type of Heaven, is called the <hi>holy City,</hi> Matt. 4.5. And therefore was <hi>Canaan</hi> an holy place, becauſe that Land, God had ſeparated from all Lands, to afford the viſible tokens of his gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious preſence in it, and to it, and to ſettle his Worſhip and Sanctuary in it for Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with himſelf, and to have the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> that inhabited it, a <hi>peculiar people,</hi> and ſet a-part for his own Honour and Service. But much more may the Heavenly <hi>Canaan</hi> to which the Saints go when dying, be called a <hi>Terra Sancta,</hi> a <hi>Holy Land;</hi> 'Tis ſeparated and ſet a-part for the glory of a holy God, for holy perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances, holy perſons: The God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is Holy, Holy, Holy. All that live with him there, are holy; only holy Ones enter there:
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61171:11"/>Holy Angels, Souls of <hi>juſt men made perfectly</hi> holy: Nothing <hi>defiled</hi> or <hi>defiling</hi> can there be admitted; no ſin, no Sinner, no more of unholineſs is there, than of unhappineſs; ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and ſin came, and ſhall go together: There, as all tears ſhall be wiped away from the eyes, ſo all ſin perfectly waſht away from the Soul: there ſhall neither be ſin in the Soul, nor Sinner in the Company: as compleat an Holineſs as God will, and we can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was <hi>terra deſiderii,</hi> ſo called,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 106.24, a <hi>pleaſant</hi> delightful Land, deſcribed to be a Land of <hi>milk and honey,</hi> and to have an affluence of all things deſirable to ſenſe, as Corn, Wine, Balm, Oil, Fountains, Paſtures. But what a faint reſemblance do all theſe carry to the pleaſures of the Heavenly <hi>Canaan?</hi> Here are the true, full and everlaſting pleaſures, fulneſs <hi>of joy, pleaſures for evermore,</hi> Eternal ſatisfaction without any ſatiety and glutting. An Eternal fulneſs, and yet an eternal freſhneſs of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights. All comforts are centred in God. All ſweetneſs and delights meet in him. In him there's infinitely more than the Soul can want or wiſh; and he is in heaven perfectly enjoyed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61171:12"/>even to the utmoſt extent of the Souls capacity; but yet the Oyl will be infinitely more plentiful than the Veſſels are capacious, which cannot hold all that oyl of joy that God can give out of himſelf. The people of God in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, are ſaid to <hi>enter into their Maſters joy,</hi> for their joy cannot fully enter into them there. In Heaven there's that we call <hi>enough,</hi> a thing never to be had in this world; there is in that Life <hi>mors deſiderii,</hi> the death of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire; and perfect joy is nothing but the ceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all our wiſhes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> The <hi>Application</hi> of all this, ſhall on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be to counſel you, To labour that your <hi>departure</hi> out of this world may be an happy <hi>Exodus,</hi> or departure; as a going from the Land of <hi>Egypt,</hi> to a happy, an heavenly <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan.</hi> And for the making this Counſel the more effectual, I'le preſent it to you in theſe four branches.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Be ſure you be <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> otherwiſe there is no entring into <hi>Canaan</hi> when you depart hence. <hi>Canaan</hi> was a <hi>Land of Promiſe,</hi> but promiſed only to <hi>Iſrael;</hi> and for your entrance into the heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> there is no promiſe unleſs you be <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> Nor is it enough for you to be carnal <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> I mean only ſuch
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:61171:12"/>in regard of outward priviledges, and enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of outward Ordinances. Outward pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges put luſt to no pain. The moſt emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for priviledges are oft under the preva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency of corruptions: But you muſt be, as Chriſt ſpeaks of <hi>Nathaneel,</hi> truly and <hi>indeed Iſraelites:</hi> Otherwiſe <hi>Publicans</hi> and Harlots <hi>enter into Heaven before a</hi> meerly nominal <hi>Iſraelite.</hi> How woful is that Hell into which men fall by preſuming of Heaven! The <hi>Valley of Viſion</hi> hath the heavieſt burden. The deeper a ſhip is laden, even with Gold, the deeper ſhe ſinks. God is moſt diſhonour'd by the ſins of viſible Profeſſours; by theſe the power of Godlineſs is oft moſt bitterly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. He that was <hi>born after the fleſh,</hi> was the greateſt perſecutor of him that was <hi>born after the ſpirit.</hi> The priviledges of grace, without the grace of the priviledg, give no admiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on into Glory. True holineſs only is the way to true happineſs. No grace but tried grace enters into Heaven. Many of the <hi>children of the Kingdom</hi> ſhall be ſhut out of the Kingdom. <hi>He is not an Iſraelite who is one outwardly, but he is an Iſraelite who is one inwardly, Rom.</hi> 2.28. <hi>The children of the fleſh, are not the children of God, Rom.</hi> 9.8. <hi>Luk.</hi> 16.25, I read of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:61171:13"/>a Son of <hi>Abraham</hi> in Hell. The children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> have oft been the children of the <hi>Devil.</hi> No promiſe of ſalvation is made more to the Member of a viſible Church, unleſs he have a changed heart, than to an Heathen.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, Take heed of <hi>turning in your hearts,</hi> back again into <hi>Egypt;</hi> many that went out of <hi>Egypt</hi> did not go into <hi>Canaan;</hi> the Holy Ghoſt tells us, how forward they were to return back into <hi>Egypt, Numb.</hi> 14.3, 4. Turn not from your profeſſions, imbrace not the <hi>preſent world,</hi> take heed of being backſliders; better you had never gone out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> than to turn back again into it. You muſt <hi>hold it out unto the death,</hi> if you would have a <hi>Crown of life;</hi> it is not he that <hi>ſets out firſt,</hi> but he that <hi>holds out laſt,</hi> that ſhall be crowned.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly, Take heed of unbelief, diſtruſt not the promiſes that God hath made, of entring into his reſt. Unbelief was the killing, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, murthering ſin of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> they <hi>could not enter in, Heb.</hi> 3.15, <hi>becauſe of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belief;</hi> no difficulties in the <hi>way,</hi> give a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation to diſtruſt the promiſe of beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the happineſs of <hi>the end.</hi> Unbelief is the ſin that of all other diſcredits God, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects mercy offered, hinders from Salvation,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:61171:13"/>puts a neceſſity of deſtruction upon you; other ſins make us <hi>obnoxious</hi> unto death, but Unbelief makes us <hi>oppoſite</hi> unto life.</p>
            <p n="4">4thly, Think not of entring into <hi>Canaan</hi> without your <hi>Joſhua,</hi> your <hi>Jeſus;</hi> there is no getting to the heavenly <hi>Canaan,</hi> but by him. He muſt be improved in theſe two regards:</p>
            <p n="1">1. As your <hi>Conquerour,</hi> one that is to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer all the enemies you are to meet with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all in your entrance into <hi>Canaan;</hi> he only can overcome Death, Devil, Guilt; it is he <hi>who by death overcomes him that hath the power of death;</hi> he overcomes him by <hi>price,</hi> in ſatisfy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Juſtice</hi> of God; by <hi>force,</hi> in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying of his <hi>works</hi> by his <hi>Spirit</hi> in the Souls of his Saints.</p>
            <p>And 2dly, You muſt improve <hi>Jeſus</hi> not only as your <hi>Conquerour,</hi> but alſo as your <hi>Leader</hi> to follow him; they followed <hi>Joſhua</hi> into <hi>Canaan; Jeſus</hi> muſt be our <hi>Captain</hi> as well as <hi>Conquerour.</hi> Follow him as your Example. If he be not your Pattern, he never procures your Pardon. You muſt follow him in the <hi>way</hi> unto <hi>Canaan,</hi> if you expect to follow him into the <hi>bleſſedneſs</hi> of <hi>Canaan.</hi> You muſt go <hi>as he</hi> did, if <hi>whither</hi> he did; in the way of <hi>holy walking,</hi> yea in the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:61171:14"/>way of <hi>ſuffering;</hi> if he will call you to follow him through mud and bloud, take up <hi>your Croſs and follow him;</hi> you muſt <hi>ſuffer with him, if you would</hi> be <hi>glorified with</hi> him.</p>
            <p>Thus I have gone briefly over the firſt thing conſiderable in the <hi>time,</hi> when <hi>Peter</hi> endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured that they ſhould remember his holy inſtructions: We have conſidered this <hi>time</hi> firſt, as giving a <hi>Title</hi> unto Death; it is here called, <hi>a Deceaſe,</hi> an <hi>Exodus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2dly, We muſt conſider it as diſcovering the <hi>lot of Peter,</hi> an eminent Apoſtle, an excellent Servant of <hi>Jeſus</hi> in the Miniſtry; and yet here he tells you of <hi>his deceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Obſervation ſhall be by way of queſtion in alluſion to the words of <hi>Stephen, Acts</hi> 7.52, <hi>Which of the Prophets have not your fathers perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted?</hi> My Doctrinal Queſtion ſhall be this: <hi>Which of the Prophets hath not death removed?</hi> Prophets <hi>ordinary,</hi> or <hi>extraordinary,</hi> Prophets <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, and Prophets ſince Chriſt,</hi> all ſlain by Death, they <hi>are deceaſed;</hi> ſays the Apoſtle <hi>after my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe.</hi> But why is it thus? Next to the will of God and the irrevocable ſtatute of dying; Take this fourfold account of the death of the Prophets:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider them as <hi>Men.</hi> 2. As <hi>holy men.</hi> 3. As ſinful men. 4. As Miniſters of Jeſus
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:61171:14"/>Chriſt, as Prophets; And upon all theſe accounts they muſt have their <hi>deceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As <hi>men</hi> they are liable to a deceaſe their bodies are fleſh and bloud; <hi>we walk after the fleſh,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi>) that is, as to the outward-man, and ſtate of frailty &amp; mortality, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.3. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven they as well as you muſt mend their Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages of Mortality once a day at leaſt, to keep them wind-tight and water-tight, to preſerve them from an untimely diſſolution; theſe Lamps cannot burn and ſhine without your Oil; they are <hi>earthen veſſels,</hi> as the Apoſtle calls them: <hi>Peter</hi> here twice calls his body a <hi>tabernacle,</hi> and that ſhortly to be laid off; the word of Life is in the Mouths of your Prophets, but the Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cters of Death are on their foreheads. <hi>Iſidore</hi> of <hi>Peluſium</hi> his expreſſion is very apt to this purpoſe, <hi>Our diſſolution,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>doth as it were run an equal pace with our framing, or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in the womb,</hi>
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoon as you light a Candle, it is melting and declining, <hi>Poſt geneſin ſequitur exodus.</hi> Every man as <hi>born,</hi> is a dying man; even <hi>Adam</hi> in his innocency, though he had a <hi>poſſe non mori,</hi> a power not to die; yet he had not a <hi>non poſſe mori:</hi> in regard of the originals of his body, and its matter, he had a remote power
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:61171:15"/>of dying, he had the <hi>principia reſolutionis,</hi> principles of diſſolution, though in regard of his excellent Conſtitution and original Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, but eſpecially the ordination and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, he was in innocency immortal; but in our fallen-ſtate as men, born, living, we are mortal, death is natural and neceſſary: We muſt die, not becauſe we are ſick, but becauſe we live, <hi>morieris non quia aegrotas, ſed quia vivis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As they are <hi>holy men,</hi> Prophets muſt die.</p>
            <p n="1">1. They muſt be made <hi>perfectly</hi> holy, and they long to be ſo; but on this ſide the grave they cannot be ſo, they have indeed the <hi>firſt-fruits of the ſpirit,</hi> but yet the reliques of ſin, <hi>primitias ſpiritus, &amp; reliquias vetuſtatis:</hi> here they ſtrive againſt ſin, and yet do but imperfectly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer it; in Heaven they are neither conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>by ſin,</hi> nor have they the company <hi>of ſin;</hi> therefore becauſe they are holy men, that they may be perfectly ſo, and have the full crop after the firſt fruits, they muſt die.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly, Becauſe they are <hi>holy men,</hi> therefore they muſt <hi>ſee God;</hi> God will not always be without their company, the leaſt grace is too good to go to <hi>hell,</hi> and to ſtay always upon <hi>earth. Enoch walked with God, and was tranſlated;</hi> of all the Patriarchs before
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:61171:15"/>the Flood, he lived the <hi>beſt</hi> and the <hi>leaſt;</hi> holy Prophets muſt die that they may go to the perfect fruition of God.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They muſt dye, becauſe they are <hi>ſinful men.</hi> Our Apoſtle <hi>Peter,</hi> that here foretells his deceaſe, not more humbly than truly call'd himſelf a <hi>ſinful man; Depart from me, O Lord, I am a ſinful man.</hi> Sin makes all ſubject to the <hi>ſtroke,</hi> though not to the <hi>ſting</hi> of death. God hates ſin whereſoever he ſees it. Chriſt muſt dye, if ſin be but imputed; and all muſt dye, if ſin be inherent. Though death be not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Saints a <hi>curſe for</hi> ſin, yet it is a <hi>conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent of</hi> ſin; and bleſſed be God that it ſhall be the <hi>cure of</hi> ſin.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They muſt dye, becauſe they are <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Miniſters of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. God oft takes away Prophets and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, they have their <hi>deceaſe</hi> to puniſh the <hi>unprofitableneſs</hi> and <hi>unthankfulneſs</hi> of their people, that never knew how to prize and value them in the time of their enjoying them. God puts out theſe lights, becauſe you play the wantons with them. If you will be play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when you ſhould be working by the light, God ſometimes righteouſly takes away the Candle, and lets you go to bed in the
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:61171:16"/>dark, without an enlightning Miniſter.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As they are <hi>Prophets</hi> they muſt dye, becauſe they are oft as <hi>Prophets perſecuted</hi> to death. A godly Miniſter is ſet in the <hi>Forlorn Hope</hi> of the Army of Chriſts Saints; wicked men oftentimes ſhorten their lives, and would not willingly let theſe lights burn to the ſocket, but would gladly blow them out be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are burnt out: Though (bleſſed be God) we cannot ſay with <hi>Lorinus</hi> the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> upon the Text, who writes concerning the <hi>Popes,</hi> That in all their ſucceſſions from <hi>Peter</hi> to the year 1625 (though he doth moſt falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly date the ſucceſſion of the <hi>Popes</hi> from <hi>Peter</hi>) there never yet was one <hi>Pope</hi> that lived twenty-four years, (and truly he may well ſay ſo, many of them having haſtned their deaths with poiſons, others with their Murders, Sodomy, Inceſt, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther notorious Villanies, not to be named by a Miniſter of Chriſt in the Pulpit). Though bleſſed be God, I ſay, we cannot ſay that none of our Miniſters have arrived to the age of 24 years in their Miniſtry; yet we muſt ſay, their Lives are commonly ſhorter than thoſe of others, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven in regard of that Antichriſtian fury prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally bent againſt them, the edg whereof hath frequently cut the thread of their Lives;
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:61171:16"/>Perſecutors have made faithful Miniſters the very Butts of their ſhot of Oppoſition: The Thief hates and ſtrikes at the Candle more than any thing; The Wolf is moſt angry with the Shepherd that defends the Flock, witneſs the rage of the Devil in all places and ages.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They muſt die as <hi>Prophets,</hi> Miniſters, becauſe there is no other way ſo fit for <hi>wicked</hi> men themſelves to praiſe and prize them, as by their dying. While godly Miniſters Lived, though they were the marks of all the Oblo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quie and oppreſſion of wicked men; yet when dead, even the wicked themſelves will give them a good Report. You read of the <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchres of the Prophets,</hi> that the <hi>Phariſees</hi> gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed; when they were alive, they perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted them, but after their deaths they garniſhed and adorned their Sepulchres. And the truth is, a <hi>dead</hi> Prophet is commonly the only praiſed Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet by a wicked man; when living, he reprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and roared againſt a wicked mans ſins out of the Pulpit; then how did the wicked ſcorn him and ſcoff at him; but when a faithful Miniſter is gone, and the Sinner ſees him quiet, and hears him ſay nothing againſt his Impieties, for faſhion-ſake at leaſt he will give him the good word of the Age and Countrey. When <hi>Sampſons</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:61171:17"/>Lion was alive and roared upon him, <hi>Sampſon</hi> rends and tears him; but when the Lion was dead, then <hi>Sampſon</hi> takes Hony out of him, and counts him a creature of ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: ſo a dead Prophet ſhall be counted ſweet, when alive he was the bittereſt and moſt unpleaſing perſon in the World to a Sinner.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They muſt die as they are <hi>Prophets,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe perhaps their <hi>own Friends</hi> have idoliz'd them, and put them in the room of God, who <hi>can,</hi> though ordinarily he <hi>will</hi> not, do his work without them: God uſes Tools, not to help <hi>him,</hi> but to make <hi>them</hi> helpful; he will not have the Servant advanced above himſelf, nor the man above the Maſter; the way to be <hi>without</hi> Miniſters, is to think you <hi>cannot be</hi> without them: the Sun needs not the <hi>Glow-worm</hi> to give it light, nor doth God need the Miniſter. God doth nothing <hi>with means,</hi> but he can do the ſame <hi>without</hi> them: there was <hi>Light</hi> before there was a <hi>Sun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. As <hi>Prophets</hi> they muſt dye, for they are to receive a <hi>Prophets reward,</hi> a <hi>Crown of glory that fadeth not away,</hi> as the Apoſtle expreſſes it, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4. &amp; 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.7, 8, a <hi>Crown of righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs.</hi> This is their working-time, it is not
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61171:17"/>the time of their reward. The righteous Judg will ſhortly pay them; they <hi>labour in the Lord,</hi> and therefore <hi>dye in the Lord,</hi> and their work is not <hi>in vain in the Lord.</hi> My <hi>labour is with the Lord</hi> (ſaith the Prophet). They are a ſweet <hi>ſavour unto God, in them that pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh.</hi> Their labour <hi>for</hi> the Lord, is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenc'd by their enjoyment <hi>of</hi> the Lord. <hi>Come well done good and faithful Servant, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into thy Maſters joy,</hi> ſhall one day be the <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge,</hi> the Recompencing-expreſſion of Jeſus Chriſt to his faithful Miniſters. They ſerve the beſt Maſter, who gives them the <hi>beſt work,</hi> the <hi>beſt wages,</hi> and is the only Maſter that gives <hi>ſtrength;</hi> and though he <hi>gives it,</hi> he <hi>rewards</hi> it after he hath given the <hi>ſtrength,</hi> and the <hi>heart</hi> to uſe it.</p>
            <p n="6">6. As <hi>Prophets</hi> they <hi>die,</hi> becauſe God will often have them <hi>preach</hi> by their <hi>death,</hi> whether violent or natural. I admired Doctor <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> more in a ſick-Chamber, and on a Death<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed, than ever I did in the Pulpit; how au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly did he read the Lecture of <hi>Patience,</hi> when he had pains, as he himſelf wrote, <hi>as great as fleſh and blood could bear!</hi> even then, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member not that by any geſture or groan he expreſt any diſlike of Gods dealings! God
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61171:18"/>will break the Box of a godly Miniſters body, that ſo the fragrant Perfumes of his Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, his Graces and Faith, may breathe out when the Box is broken. I add,</p>
            <p n="7">7. They muſt <hi>die</hi> as <hi>Prophets</hi> and <hi>Miniſters,</hi> becauſe often the labour of their Miniſtry <hi>ſhortens</hi> their days; they ſpend their Oil in giving you light; like Clouds they diſſolve themſelves by dropping upon their too-often barren Hearers. Nothing wearies and wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens the body more than Study. I have look'd upon other Callings, as Recreations to the Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of a ſtudious Miniſter, that labours in hunting, before he brings you Veniſon. A Knife is <hi>always</hi> better and <hi>often</hi> more worn by uſe and cutting, than by lying ſtill and ruſting. Doctor <hi>Whitaker,</hi> that Learned and famous Servant of God in his Generation, (who for Learning, Orthodox parts, and Zeal, was the <hi>terror</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Ornament</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> ſometimes Maſter of <hi>St. John</hi>'s in <hi>Cambridge;</hi> of whom <hi>Bellarmine</hi> himſelf ſaid, having his picture hung up in his Study, Though he was a <hi>Heretick,</hi> yet he was a <hi>learned Heretick</hi>); This bleſſed <hi>Whitaker</hi> was ſo painful a Student, and ſat up ſo late in Nights at Study, that he ſaid of himſelf when
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61171:18"/>he felt his ſtrength decaying, and his ſickneſs encreaſing, He would willingly part with all that Learning that ever he got by Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, upon the condition he could recover that ſtrength and health that he had loſt by Candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light. The Prophets ſhorten their <hi>time,</hi> to bring you to <hi>Eternity.</hi> The Application follows; and it ſhall be by way of, 1. Advice, 2. Comfort.</p>
            <p n="1">1. By way of Advice; 1. If the Prophets have their <hi>deceaſe,</hi> Then they ſhould <hi>labour while they may,</hi> they ſhould work apace, they ſhall not do it long. <hi>Peter</hi> knowing that the <hi>put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting off his tabernacle</hi> did approach, was the more vigorous in his Paſtoral endeavours, <hi>v.</hi> 14. 'Tis moſt incongruous for a Miniſter to be ſure that he cannot <hi>live,</hi> and yet ſo lazy that he will not <hi>preach;</hi> Let him take heed leſt he be ſo guilty that he dares not <hi>die;</hi> What a ſhame is it that ſome called Miniſters have a greater <hi>plurality</hi> of Livings than they can promiſe to themſelves of days to live in? No preaching in the Grave, unleſs <hi>Silence</hi> preach, which I wiſh that of this Great Divine may do.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Magiſtrates ſhould labour to keep up and encourage a Succeſſion of Learned and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>borious Miniſters; ſo far ſhould they be from perſecuting, oppoſing them, and drying up their
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61171:19"/>Oil of Maintenance, that they ſhould encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and highly honour them, not only for their works-ſake already performed, but that they may perform it ſtill; and not only give them a <hi>liberty</hi> to preach ſtill, but a <hi>liberal Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> for preaching. A Magiſtrate as well as a Miniſter ſhould endeavour that <hi>Sanctity</hi> ſhould be tranſmitted to Poſterity.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>People ſhould</hi> improve their Miniſters if they muſt have a <hi>deceaſe;</hi> You have but borrowed your Books, therefore you had need read them the faſter. Walk <hi>while it is light;</hi> let not your Miniſter go till he <hi>hath bleſſed you</hi> with ſome ſpiritual Bleſſing; ſhorten not his Life with grief for your unprofitableneſs. You tear your Books apace, and wear out your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters; for ſhame learn your Leſſons.</p>
            <p n="4">4. If Miniſters have their <hi>deceaſe,</hi> May thoſe that <hi>ſucceed</hi> them in <hi>place</hi> endeavour to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, yea, to exceed them in <hi>worth</hi> and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity. May that expreſſion of the Antient here take place: <hi>Cum fortes ad proemia vocat, debi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les ad certamina roborat; Cum iſtos ſuſcipiendo remunerat, hiſce laborum vires quas remuneret, ſubminiſtrat:</hi> When God Crowns ſome for work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, may he ſtrengthen others for their work. May we never be miſerable in having Reeds
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61171:19"/>in the room of Pillars: And may you of this Congregation with Wiſdom and unanimity make choice of <hi>ſuch a perſon</hi> to ſucceed Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor <hi>Seaman,</hi> as may ſo fill and become his Pulpit; that if poſſible you may be ſenſible of a <hi>change</hi> rather than a <hi>loſs</hi> by Doctor <hi>Seaman</hi>'s <hi>deceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Muſt Miniſters <hi>die? Pray for them</hi> to him that hath the power of Life and Death. It was <hi>Paul</hi>'s great Prayer to be pray'd for; 'Twas through Prayer that he truſted <hi>to be given to them,</hi> Phil. 2.2. 'Twill be your deſerved trouble when your faithful Miniſters die, that you while they lived pray'd no more <hi>for,</hi> and profited no more <hi>by</hi> them (and theſe two have a common Conjunction): Prayer is the mean to <hi>get</hi> Miniſters when we <hi>want</hi> them, and to <hi>keep</hi> them when we <hi>have</hi> them.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Muſt Miniſters die, <hi>Maintain them</hi> while they ſtay. The unkind World <hi>ſtorms</hi> them, do not you <hi>ſtarve</hi> them, or hinder them from Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying by your neglecting to ſupply them. I neither ſpeak, nor have <hi>cauſe</hi> to ſpeak in this kind for my ſelf: but for my <hi>Brethrens</hi>-ſake, I cannot be ſilent. Make that Proverb ceaſe; <hi>London loves a Cheap Goſpel.</hi> The <hi>beſt</hi> of Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters <hi>walk in the fleſh;</hi> acknowledg this as your
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61171:20"/>
               <hi>priviledg,</hi> but ſuch as points to your <hi>Duty.</hi> If they die, let not your penuriouſneſs be the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeaſe of which they die. Conſider they will not long be chargeable.</p>
            <p n="7">7. Laſtly, Muſt the <hi>beſt</hi> of Miniſters dye? Be willing <hi>to follow them.</hi> The ſweeteſt Flowers wither ſooneſt. God takes away the beſt of his Servants, his <hi>Enochs,</hi> often haſtily; why do we love ſo much then to linger behind? We ſhould like the world the leſs <hi>while</hi> we ſtay, and the <hi>leſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to</hi> ſtay in it, becauſe holy men and Miniſters ſo ſpeedily forſake it. We delight not in a room without furniture, nor in an houſe that hath on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly naked walls. Sanctity is the beſt furniture of <hi>ſouls,</hi> and Saints of <hi>places,</hi> both for <hi>uſe</hi> and <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament;</hi> why do we then love ſo much to ſtay, when they are taken down? And of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, we Miniſters (methinks) ſhould be moſt willing to follow our Brethren, and dear Companions in the Miniſtry, by long acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, frequent and indearing viſits, ſweet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent chearfulneſs, fraternal counfels, learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed debates, prayer, yea promiſes and re-pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of prayer, of late ſo nearly linkt and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timately twiſted to and with us. Sometimes, methinks, when I recall (<hi>them</hi> I cannot) the <hi>memories</hi> of the great <hi>Gouge</hi> and <hi>Gataker,</hi> the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61171:20"/>holy and delightful <hi>Whitaker,</hi> the prudent <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamy,</hi> that man of Prayer <hi>Aſh,</hi> and of Tears <hi>Nalton,</hi> that ſweet name and man of affection <hi>Love,</hi> whoſe great <hi>love</hi> to me was match'd with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more than my <hi>fidelity</hi> to him (and I would kiſs even the feet (though elſe I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly deſpiſe the tongue) of Calumny, would they be, which yet they never durſt be, the bearers to me of the leaſt proof to the contrary); alſo of learned <hi>Cranford,</hi> true-hearted <hi>Taylor,</hi> victorious <hi>Vines,</hi> laborious and upright <hi>Jackſon,</hi> richly adorned <hi>Drake,</hi> who knew every thing better than his own rare accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; <hi>Marſhal</hi> that Maſter in the art of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Burroughs</hi> another great ornament of the Pulpit, judicious and painful <hi>Caryl,</hi> that great Pattern of induſtry and ſanctity, Doctor <hi>Wilkin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> and now laſtly the profound Doctor <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man:</hi> When (I ſay) I recall the <hi>memories</hi> of theſe now bleſſed Worthies, I am ready to ſay, Lord, why do I long no more to get among them! and yet what are theſe to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> for draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out my affection and longings for Heaven! in whom are centred all the excellencies of theſe, and of all thoſe millions of Saints that have been from the beginning of the world, that now are, or ever ſhall be; and compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to him, are no more than the faint and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61171:21"/>feeble flame of the ſmalleſt Candle to the Sun when ſhining forth in greateſt glory! and without whom, Heaven it ſelf with all its o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther furniture of Saints and Angels, deckt with the moſt ſhining Attire of all their poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible perfections, would be but as a ſheet of Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers without a figure, and could entertain us only with pleaſures, in the notion, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights of meer Imagination.</p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall ſhut up this Point concerning the deceaſe of godly Miniſters, with but na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming a ſecond Uſe by way of Relief and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment; For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Though the Prophets of God do die, yet the <hi>God</hi> of thoſe Prophets never dies: He is the <hi>living God,</hi> and <hi>only hath immortality.</hi> Though the Streams be dried up, the Fountain hath a conſtant fulneſs, out of which the faithful may draw all ſupplies of <hi>Grace</hi> and Comfort, by a due improvement of the Promiſes, and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing up Communion with God, who obligeth us indeed to the participation of the Miniſtry when we may enjoy it; yet never tied him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from exhibiting to his people, even in the drieſt Wilderneſs, the ſweeteſt and fountainous delights of ſpecial grace and goodneſs.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Though the Propets die, yet the <hi>Souls</hi>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:61171:21"/>of the Prophets die not. Their <hi>deceaſe</hi> is the <hi>Exodus</hi> or <hi>departure</hi> of their Souls to God, with whom they reſt for ever after their ſhort la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours in this troubleſome World. The <hi>Jewel</hi> is laid up in a better ſtate, than when it was in the torn feeble Casket of their Bodies.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Though the Prophets die, yet (in a ſenſe) the <hi>ſons</hi> of the Prophets die not. There ſhall be ſucceſſively a Miniſtry, and Miniſters, to the end of the World. <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath promiſed to be <hi>with</hi> them, and therefore certainly they ſhall <hi>be,</hi> even to that period. His Ordinances ſhall continue <hi>till the Lord come,</hi> and therefore there ſhall <hi>be</hi> diſpenſers of them: He will have an <hi>Houſe</hi> always, and therefore <hi>Stewards</hi> ever in it. Let the Devil and Antichriſt rage and puff never ſo furiouſly, they ſhall never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguiſh the light of the Miniſtry. Could they have accompliſht that deſign, it had been done above a thouſand years ago.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Though the Prophets die, yet their <hi>me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory</hi> dies not: The fragrancy of their names like a precious Ointment breathes forth even <hi>af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> yea, <hi>by</hi> the breaking the brittle boxes of their bodies. Their heavenly Inſtructions, or Writings, or Examples, at leaſt live when they are dead. And thus this eminent Servant of <hi>Chriſt</hi> dies not.</p>
            <pb n="42" facs="tcp:61171:22"/>
            <p n="5">5. Though the <hi>Prophets</hi> die, yet their <hi>Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> do not die: Though they paſs away as <hi>a wind,</hi> yet their words neither are but <hi>wind,</hi> nor paſs away as ſuch. Their word whereby they <hi>convert</hi> Souls, dies not as to the effect thereof, Grace in the Soul. Their <hi>threatning</hi> words for ſin die not. <hi>The Prophets do they live for ever? Zech.</hi> 1.5. <hi>But my words and my ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes which I commanded by my Servants the Prophets, did they not take hold of your fathers?</hi> The <hi>Word of God,</hi> even in this ſenſe, may be ſaid not <hi>to be bound,</hi> namely, to the abode of the <hi>Prophets</hi> upon Earth: Threatned Sinners ſhall know by feeling the Truth threatned, that <hi>they have had a Prophet among them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. In the third and laſt place we conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed theſe words, <hi>After my deceaſe,</hi> as intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>the ſeaſon</hi> deſigned by <hi>Peter</hi> for benefiting the Church, and that was <hi>after his deceaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And from this my third and laſt Obſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an is, <hi>It is the Duty of the ſervants of God, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially Miniſters, to endeavour that they may ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly benefit others, even after their deaths. The things that thou haſt heard of me, commit to faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 2 Tim. 2.2.). Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which words Reverend <hi>Calvin</hi> well notes: Here the Apoſtle ſhews, <hi>Quantum ſit ſolicitus
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61171:22"/>de propaganda ſana doctrina ad poſteros,</hi> His <hi>ſollicitouſneſs, to propagate ſound Doctrine to Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity;</hi> and that the Servant of Chriſt muſt not only <hi>quamdiu vivit, while he lives,</hi> labour to preſerve the purity of Doctrine, <hi>ſed quam longiſſime ejus cura &amp; ſtudiam ſe extendere poterit,</hi> as far as ever his care and ſtudy ſhould be able to extend. The like ſome Learned men have obſerved upon 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.14. <hi>Keep this Commandment without ſpot and unrebukable, until the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> No faithful Servant of Chriſt is willing that the fruit of his Endowments or Employments ſhould die with him, but that they may live when he is dead, for the furthering your Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; that <hi>Inſtructions</hi> may abide with you to inform you, <hi>Exhortations</hi> to <hi>quicken</hi> you, <hi>Examples</hi> (if holy) to be <hi>imitated</hi> by you: his <hi>ſufferings</hi> for the Truth to <hi>ſtrengthen</hi> and confirm you in the Truth thereby ſealed.</p>
            <p>And this is their Duty, Firſt, That thereby they may keep <hi>up</hi> the <hi>name of God,</hi> and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote his glory in the World. This we ſhould deſire may be done after our death, yea by it. It was excellent Counſel of <hi>Luther, Diſce mori ut vivat Chriſti gloria, Learn to die that the glory of Chriſt may live.</hi> If Chriſt may increaſe, by
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61171:23"/>or after our decreaſe, our very diminution ſhould be our Option; whatever makes Chriſt great, ſhould pleaſe us. The end of living or dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is Gods glory; if living or dying <hi>we are the Lords,</hi> our living and dying ſhould be to <hi>the Lord;</hi> we ſhould <hi>ſerve our generation,</hi> that the generations after us may <hi>ſerve him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Hereby the Servants of God beſt <hi>provide for their own names:</hi> 'Tis this that makes our names to be a ſweet Perfume to Poſterity, and gives them as much of Eternity as in this World they are capable of obtaining. The <hi>rotting</hi> of the name is a wicked mans Curſe; and the preſervation of our memories by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good, is both a <hi>Duty,</hi> and a <hi>Bleſſing.</hi> As an uſeleſs, unſerviceable perſon is dead while he lives, ſo ſervice is that that makes us live when we are dead; and makes the places where we lived like the Civet-box when the Civet is taken out of it, to ſavour of our holy Endeavours when we our ſelves are gone from and out of them.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thirdly, <hi>Love to Souls</hi> makes this a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; Regard to theſe muſt be lengthened be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the length of our lives. A Servant of Chriſt muſt do good to as many as he can. 'Tis both his duty and diſpoſition. <hi>Paul</hi> tells
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61171:23"/>us, the deſign of all his condeſcenſions was, that he might <hi>gain the more,</hi> 1 Cor. 9.19. No godly man needs or wiſhes to make a Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poly of Heaven. Every Saint loves Company to Glory; he loves to be ſaved <hi>ſurely,</hi> but not <hi>ſolitarily.</hi> 'Tis this that ſhould be the great motive to <hi>writing,</hi> to benefit others after our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe. The Pen hath (as one ſpeaks) the greateſt Auditories, and the advantage of levening Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity with Holineſs; and it hath given the deepeſt wounds to Antichriſt, and been the beſt Antidote againſt Hereſies. 'Tis a holy Covetouſneſs to crave the ſaving of many, both while we live, and after death. Beſides, this is a kind of countermining of Satan, who after the death of able Inſtruments, labours moſt to pervert the Truth, and to ſubvert Souls. <hi>After my departure</hi> (ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> Acts 20.29.) <hi>grievous Wolves ſhall enter in among you, not ſparing the flock.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Fourthly, The beſt in their life-time have done <hi>too little</hi> for the good of Souls. How ſmall is the number of thoſe we have brought to Heaven, compared with thoſe, that for ought we know we have undone for ever by our ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Examples, and <hi>other encouragements to ſin!</hi> There may be ſeveral that ſhall be ſaved, who
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61171:24"/>have occaſioned the damnation of others by their ſinful and ſcandalous carriages. The colder the Winter hath been, the hotter (ſay ſome) the Summer is like to be; ſo the more benummed and frozen our endeavours for ſaving of Souls, have been formerly, the hotter ſhould our Divine Zeal be afterwards to ſave them: Never did a bad man do more againſt Chriſt than <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>before</hi> his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion; but never did a good man do more for him than <hi>Paul</hi> did <hi>afterwards; I would to God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that all that hear me were ſuch as I am. As much as in me is,</hi> (Rom. 1.15.) <hi>I will preach the Goſpel. I will gladly ſpend and be ſpent,</hi> 2 Cor. 12.15. <hi>The grace of God was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding abundant in that faith and love,</hi> 1 Tim. 1.14. which anſwered, the former to his <hi>infidelity,</hi> the latter to his <hi>perſecution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Fifthly, The <hi>reward</hi> that godly men and Prophets expect is <hi>Everlaſting.</hi> It ſhall laſt longer than their longeſt uſefulneſs can do; their Crown ſhall never fade away. Why then ſhould their helpfulneſs to Souls be ſhort upon earth, ſince their happineſs in Heaven ſhall be perpetual? And 'tis the opinion of ſome, That the Saints in Heaven have an addi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion made to their happineſs there, by the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:61171:24"/>Converſion of every Soul that is converted by their means after their departure.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Laſtly, In ſome regards they may do good to Souls <hi>after their deceaſe,</hi> with <hi>leſs diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage</hi> than they could while living upon earth; for while here they lived, their <hi>bodily preſence and ſpeech was weak and contemptible;</hi> their outward man, their conſtant familiar Converſe with a people, made them the more neglected: But theſe hinderances after death are removed, people then being ready to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain more honourable thoughts of them, than when they lived. Every advantage for doing good ſhould be embraced. The higher thoughts any have of us, the higher thoughts we ſhould labour, that thereby they may have of Chriſt. <hi>Paul</hi> his <hi>bodily preſence</hi> was deſpicable; but how greatly have his <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi> benefited Poſterity!</p>
            <p n="1">1. For the Uſe of this Point.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Heinous is the impiety of thoſe who ſo <hi>live,</hi> that they do more hurt to Souls <hi>after their</hi> death, than ever they did while they lived; whoſe practical immoralities, and he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retical opinions, being tranſmitted to poſterity, prove its bane and poyſon. I might inſtance in <hi>Arrius, Pelagius, Socinus, Arminius,</hi> and
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:61171:25"/>other Innovators, who by their Writings have perverted more, ſince they left the world, than ever they did by their tongues while they were in it; and what rebuke I give to Hetero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox <hi>Writings,</hi> is as due to thoſe Heterodox (by ſome ſo called) <hi>Practices</hi> of impiety, wherewith men are deſtructive to thoſe who follow their Examples in after-ages. Our practices while we live, ſhould be ſo holy and exemplary, that when we dye, we may not be aſham'd to ſay, we deſire that <hi>after our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe theſe things may be remembred.</hi> Who ever heard of any impure Senſualiſt, or any infamous for immoralities, to be ſo ſenſleſly impudent, as to ſay, <hi>Let poſterity have theſe things always in remembrance?</hi> for by the ſame reaſon that they deſire to hide their impieties in <hi>ſecrecy</hi> while they <hi>live,</hi> they will wiſh to bury them in <hi>Oblivion</hi> when they are <hi>dead.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. If it were the duty of the now deceaſed Saints while here they continued with us, to endeavour the ſpiritual welfare of thoſe they left behind them, by what they were, and did; 'tis doubtleſs <hi>our</hi> duty who are Survivers, to recall and recollect the Excellent accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments and performances of thoſe deceaſed
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:61171:25"/>Saints, we cannot be benefited <hi>by</hi> them, if we be not mindful <hi>of</hi> them; nor will their worth be <hi>imitated</hi> by us, if it be not <hi>remembred</hi> by us; nor ſhall we bleſs God <hi>the father of lights, and the giver of every good and perfect gift,</hi> for giving gifts and Graces to men, unleſs we <hi>acknowledg</hi> their gifts and Graces; nor do we duly <hi>encourage</hi> our ſelves or others to endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour the welfare of Poſterity, if we obſerve not the honour that Uſefulneſs hath refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted upon thoſe that went before us. And we are wanting in our reſpect to the memory of deceaſed Saints, if we bury their <hi>Names</hi> with their <hi>Bodies;</hi> it being as true a duty to <hi>preſerve</hi> the <hi>former,</hi> as to <hi>interr</hi> the <hi>latter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ANd the due reſentment of this true, yea, important duty, engageth me to preſent you with a <hi>glimpſe</hi> of thoſe excellent endowments and performances, that rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adorned the <hi>Soul</hi> and <hi>Converſation</hi> of this famous and worthy Servant of Chriſt, Doctor <hi>Lazarus Seaman.</hi> Of theſe, in ſome reſpects, I am as fit as moſt to ſpeak, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of my intimate acquaintance with him; though in other regards, I may poſſibly be deemed the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitteſt of any, becauſe the known affection that was between us, may ſeem to make me partial (which yet I
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:61171:26"/>ſhall not be) in commending him above his worth and deſert. This man of God, as he ſeemed to ſome to reſemble that great Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> in his <hi>life-time,</hi> who was an <hi>auſtere man, and ſubject to paſſions</hi> (for elſe he had not been a man, and natural ſweetneſs never ſaved, nor did its defect ever damn, any Saint:) ſo did he truly reſemble him in his <hi>departure,</hi> he having in his aſcent let fall his <hi>Mantle;</hi> (Oh that ſome <hi>Eliſha</hi> might take it up, and ſucceed him with a <hi>double portion of his Spirit!</hi>) his <hi>Mantle,</hi> I ſay, (that, I mean, of his ſweet memorial) he hath let fall among us, and that ſo richly <hi>perfumed,</hi> that it muſt a little, though but a little while perfume the Pulpit where now I ſtand, and the place where now I Preach. I ſhall therefore view and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the excellent endowments, and great worth of this deceaſed Servant of Chriſt, as they are conſiderable in ſundry of thoſe his Capacities, in which (while living and dying) he was concerned. And,</p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall conſider him as concerned in the <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logical School.</hi> And here I am not a little afraid to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into ſo large a field, leſt I ſhould therein loſe both my ſelf and you; and indeed ſo I ſhould, if I deſign'd to expatiate upon the whole field of his Scholaſtical worth, (a task to me impoſſible) and not rather to walk in the known and beaten path of his ordinarily-under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood abilities. He was a Perſon of a <hi>moſt deep, pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing,</hi> and eagle-ey'd Judgment in all points of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal Divinity. He had few Equals, if any Superiors, in ability to decide and determine a dark and doubtful Controverſie. He could ſtate a Theological queſtion with admirable clearneſs and acuteneſs, and knew how in a Controverſie to cleave (as we ſay) an hair. Nor was he leſs able to defend than to finde out the truth:
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:61171:26"/>He was (I had almoſt ſaid) an invincible Diſputant; his Conqueſts were as many as were his Contentions with any adverſaries of the truth; and ſo conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous were his abilities herein, that he ſometimes diſheartned Oppoſers in their very entrance into the liſts of Diſputation with him. As a taſte hereof, I ſhall preſent you with this inſtance.</p>
            <p>There was a Noble Family, the Governeſs whereof, a Right Honorable Lady, being often ſolicited by ſome Romiſh Prieſts to embrace their falſe Religion, It was thought fit that before there ſhould be a conſent to ſuch a Solicitation, ſome Learned Proteſtant Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine ſhould be deſired to Diſpute ſome points of Popiſh Controverſies with the Romiſh Prieſts, in the preſence of the Lord and Lady, for their further ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in Religion. A Friend of the Lady adviſed her to make choice of Mr. <hi>Seaman</hi> (for this agitation was long before he proceeded Doctor), who undertakes the conflict with the Prieſts. The meeting for Diſputation being agreed upon, Mr. <hi>Seaman,</hi> and two Popiſh Prieſts (the ableſt that could be found) came to the Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man's Houſe, where being met, Mr. <hi>Seaman</hi> (too ſoon diſcovering his Learning and Abilities) having uſed all the means imaginable to engage them in a Diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, firſt by ſtating the Queſtion, the wary Seducers who (like the firſt of their Order that made his onſet upon the <hi>Woman</hi>) delight only to go over <hi>where the hedg is loweſt;</hi> or like the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> to fight when there are no <hi>Swords in Iſrael;</hi> theſe Prieſts (I ſay) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving the great abilities of their Antagoniſt, and conſcious either of their own, or of the weakneſs of their Cauſe, or (as 'tis moſt probable) of both; after all endeavours and provocations that in Civility
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:61171:27"/>could be uſed, declined the queſtion, (which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi>) and would never be brought ſo much as to the ſtating of it, much leſs to endure the ſhock of an Argument, but ſhamefully quitted the field, and durſt never either give or take the ſtroke of a formed Syllogiſm. They who were Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly inclined, hereupon ſtood amazed to ſee the Cowardlineſs of their Champions, and ever after ('tis thought) grew cooler in their affections to Popery, till at length they grew hot (as ſtill they are) againſt it.</p>
            <p>Did I deſire to enlarge upon this head of Doctor <hi>Seaman</hi>'s abilities in Polemical Divinity, I might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in that his Learned Performance, the Divinity-Act, which he kept in the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridg,</hi> when he proceeded Doctor. This Degree he took by performing his Exerciſes appointed by the Statutes of the Univerſity, (the obtaining that Degree by the favour of Majeſty, the fountain of Honour, being termed by Biſhop <hi>Brownrig,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der for Wit and Learning, rather the receiving a kind of <hi>dubbing</hi> or <hi>Knighthood,</hi> than a taking the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree of a Doctor of Divinity, though I interpoſe not my thoughts in the leaſt herein, as not knowing the important Reaſons that have induced all men to this manner of proceeding.) And ſo Learnedly did he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend his Poſition that was the ſubject of Diſputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in that Act, that he repelled all the Arguments brought againſt it with great ſtrength and dexterity in his anſwers. And by occaſion of my mentioning that his Divinity-Act, I ſhall only ſignifie, That the deſign of his Poſition which therein he maintained, was to aſſert the Providence of God in diſpoſing of Political Governments; a Point till that time little ſtudied,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:61171:27"/>and not ſo well underſtood, though ſince that time ſeveral have received light therein <hi>from this burning and ſhining light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. I ſhall a while conſider this worthy man, as concerned in his <hi>Paſtoral Employment</hi> and capacity. And here,</p>
            <p>Firſt, I preſent him to you as a moſt excellent and profound <hi>Caſuiſt.</hi> And indeed his great Skill in Caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtical Divinity, was by ſome eſteemed the Maſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece of his Learning; and I knew none more eminent therein, than was Doctor <hi>Seaman,</hi> in regard whereof our loſs of ſuch an uſeful man is much to be lamented; for one of the greateſt defects of Theological Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, is commonly thought to be that of Caſuiſts; though the uſefulneſs of Caſuiſtical Divines be as great as their rarity, both for directing and eaſing of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, a thing little regarded in theſe dayes of <hi>Latitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarianiſm,</hi> (O uncouth, and till of late unheard-of word! (how it ſounds!) horrid to the ears of (Pious) <hi>Grammarians,</hi> giving too much eaſe to <hi>Practice,</hi> but too little to <hi>Pronunciation</hi>). And I much doubt, (or rather doubt not at all) whether any Divine in <hi>London</hi> was ſo much ſought unto, for reſolving of difficult caſes, as was Doctor <hi>Seaman;</hi> who for his abilities herein was famous to my knowledg above thirty years ago, and ſince that time, how great proficiency a perſon of <hi>his</hi> parts and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtry might and did make in that noble Piece of Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy (for the talleſt in that part of Learning, may grow taller) any may eaſily conceive, and none I am confident ſo happily underſtood, as you that enjoy'd the benefit of his conſtant Preaching.</p>
            <p>Secondly Further, as to his <hi>Paſtoral Office,</hi> he was a Perſon moſt able and dextrous in the <hi>expounding</hi> of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:61171:28"/>
               <hi>Scripture;</hi> one that could as well reach and fathom the difficult places thereof as any I ever heard, either in a <hi>Pulpit</hi> or private <hi>diſcourſe:</hi> He was an <hi>Interpreter</hi> (I may truly ſay) <hi>one of a thouſand,</hi> and one that could give the mind of the holy Ghoſt with much clearneſs and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicuity. Of this you that are now my mournful, and of late his delighted Hearers, can give (as ſundry of you of late have given me) the beſt and moſt ſatisfactory ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, being ſo experimentally acquainted with the Truth I now utter; which I the rather believe, becauſe in the mentioning thereof, I move ſo much ſorrow, which I ſee vents it ſelf by your weeping-eyes. Nor can I blame your ſorrows: For to loſe ſuch an enlightning Doctor, is (as 'twas once ſaid of the loſs of <hi>Chryſoſtom) to part with the Sun out of the Firmament.</hi> Methinks I hear you an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering to <hi>Philip</hi>'s queſtion, and in the Eunuch's words, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.31. <hi>How can we underſtand unleſs ſome man ſhould guide us?</hi> To loſe ſuch a Doctor is to loſe, if not your ſight, yet your Seer; the Lord preſerve and increaſe the former, and reſtore the latter in a Succeſſion. Doctor <hi>Seamans</hi> Sermons were not like ſome Buildings, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of old, that have ſmall and ill-contrived Lights, his Doctrinal Light being the great beauty of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, though in thoſe excellent ſtructures there was care enough taken for the Chimney too, I mean, to give the warmth of Application alſo: How eaſie did he render the moſt difficult Scriptures, ſo breaking the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſhell of the <hi>Letter,</hi> that with greateſt pleaſure you might taſt the ſweetneſs of the Kernel in the <hi>ſenſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, As a <hi>Paſtor</hi> he was a moſt <hi>Orthodox</hi> Divine and <hi>ſound in the faith.</hi> And I look upon this as his high Commendation, in the capacity of a Miniſter. And this his excellent diſcourſes of Juſtification, Faith, and the
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:61171:28"/>Covenant of Grace, which were the ſubjects of his dying Labours, here in this place, eminently declare and teſtifie. And 'tis my earneſt Requeſt, if there be any of you that have had the ability of taking thoſe Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes from him ſo exactly, that the publication of them will not be too injurious to the Doctors accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rateneſs, That you would gratifie the World with ſuch a bleſſing. And by ſo much the greater was his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendableneſs for Orthodoxy, by how much the more Heterodoxy in theſe dayes abounds, as if we were fallen at once into the ſinks of Time and Hereſie. What a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany <hi>of uncatechized <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſtarts</hi> do we now behold, vent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as confidently their heretical Notions in oppoſition to our famous Engliſh Divines, as if <hi>Jewel, Whitaker, Davenant, Downam, Renolds, Abbot, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> &amp;c. were by them to be degraded to School-boyes, and to ſit at their feet to reap the bleſſing of their heads: yea, as if to the Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England, ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion</hi> had been intended when <hi>ſubſcription</hi> was perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med; nay, as if Scripture it ſelf were to be Hector'd down <hi>by their malapert and ſaucy ignorance.</hi> Nor do I with ſo much (holy I hope) indignation mention this young <hi>brood of Theologues</hi> to expreſs the great diſparity between their and Doctor <hi>Seaman's</hi> Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtical Abilities, (Oh what poor ſhrubs are theſe to this (till death fell'd him) lofty Cedar!) as to congratulate the happineſs of this age, in enjoying the excellent Labours (thoſe poyſon-expelling Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotes) of Mr. <hi>Polhil</hi> and <hi>Antiſozzo,</hi> (the Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſt to the latter of which worthy pair of Writers, I muſt needs commend, though not for his Learning, yet for his Prudence, who paſſeth over with a chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh ſcoff inſtead of a ſcholaſtical Confutation, a Book
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:61171:29"/>that he is no more able rationally to anſwer, than to eat the paper of the whole impreſſion. But for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, I diſmiſs the Trifler, He may poſſibly be call'd for again hereafter in another way, if better Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hinder not.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, He was (as to his <hi>Paſtoral ſtation</hi>) a richly furniſh't Divine with all materials of <hi>Didactical</hi> and <hi>Practical Divinity;</hi> he was ſuch a <hi>Promptuary</hi> of all proviſions for the relief of Souls, as that I may truly ſay, he was a <hi>Scribe inſtructed to the Kingdom of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, like unto a man that is an houſholder, that bringeth out of his treaſure things new and old.</hi> I may juſtly ſay of him, That he was (as 'twas once ſaid of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther) an <hi>Ocean of Theology.</hi> And he had ſo throughly digeſted the whole body of Divinity, that he could upon all occaſions diſcourſe upon any Point without labour, and needed as little to be beholding to others for helping him to matter for his Sermons, as did any the moſt richly accompliſhed Preacher with whom I ever was (as yet) acquainted. He was one that could draw out of his richly ſtored Self, whatever was needful to draw forth to others. How unlike in this reſpect to thoſe empty and unaccompliſh'd Predicants, who Preach the Sermons of their Non-conforming Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors, upon which yet I ſhould not have reflected, (though loſers may have leave to ſpeak) did they not alſo reproach our perſons, when they Preach (to ſay no <hi>worſe</hi>) our Sermons; they practiſing that in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, which they deride when done in private, I mean, <hi>repetition of Sermons.</hi> And as our Doctor was ſo fully accompliſh'd, in carrying about with him, or rather in being (a living) Body of Divinity; ſo was it his happineſs, and as much his people's, that he did
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:61171:29"/>both fluently, and yet rationally, deliver his notions, without the leaſt impedition or heſitation; he being in this regard, <hi>not only a Scribe inſtructed</hi> for the Kingdom of Heaven, but one whoſe <hi>tongue was the Pen of a ready writer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Once more: He was a perſon of great <hi>ſtability and ſteadineſs</hi> in the truth; not a <hi>reed ſhaken with the</hi> winde, nor had he <hi>menſtruam fidem,</hi> as <hi>Tertul.</hi> ſpeaks, a Faith as changeable as the Moon. Neither Muſick nor Furnace, Flatteries nor Threats, could entice or affright him from the truth: I am confident he valued one truth of Chriſt, above all the wealth of both the <hi>Indies;</hi> he was not a ſilken <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> that would debauch his Conſcience for a Preferment. In all times, Doctor <hi>Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> contended for the ſame Verities which will al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways be the ſame, let times and intereſt be never ſo changeable.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Let us view this excellent perſon, as in <hi>the capacity of a Chriſtian,</hi> or, as concerned in the gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral practice of Chriſtianity: And ſo, Firſt, I ever obſerved in him a <hi>great contentation</hi> with his eſtate, and the allotments of Providence. He was not a
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>v.</hi> 16, one that ever I heard expreſs any complaint againſt the lot laid out for him by Providence. He was better pleas'd in being a <hi>real Paſtor</hi> to <hi>one,</hi> than a <hi>nominal Paſtor</hi> to a <hi>thouſand</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations; and was well pleas'd in living (as that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Woman ſaid) among <hi>his own People;</hi> he was always eminent as in obſervation <hi>of,</hi> ſo in ſubmiſſion to all publick Providences. As he Aſſerted Providential diſpoſal in the School, in his Diſputation, ſo in his Practice and Converſation.</p>
            <pb n="58" facs="tcp:61171:30"/>
            <p>Secondly, He was deeply and <hi>tenderly ſenſible</hi> of the ſtate of the Church of Chriſt, He was ever very inquiſitive how it fared with the people of God in foreign parts; and this not out of <hi>Athenian</hi> curioſity, but out of a publick ſpirit of Chriſtianity; and ever had he ſuitable affections to the Churches condition, proſperous or adverſe. And he was as near to <hi>Germany, France,</hi> yea, to <hi>America,</hi> in his ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathy and reſentments, as he was diſtant in place.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He was <hi>eminently open-hearted and handed too,</hi> to the eſpecially Pious Poor; he did <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulere tam modeſtiae, quum inopiae,</hi> and would regard the modeſty of a poor man, that could not be clamo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous. Of this I have been an obſerver, both as to his readineſs to relieve Miniſters, and private Chriſtians; he was <hi>ready to every good work;</hi> A <hi>ſeaſonable Grace</hi> to the preſent diſtreſſes of many eminent at once for Piety and Poverty alſo. This good man (as a cloud in <hi>Solomon</hi>'s expreſſion) emptied himſelf not only by ſhowres of Doctrine, but of Charity alſo. And there are few, I am confident, but going to him upon the occaſion of receiving relief, had their wants and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectations anſwered, to his ability.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, He was induſtrious and indefatigable in his <hi>Calling.</hi> This commends him as Scholar and Chriſtian alſo. Rarely did this ſtudious Doctor al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low himſelf any diverting recreation: The precious jewel of Time, how did he eſteem it! he would not loſe the very filings thereof. This I mention, that he may herein be a pattern; we are faln into times of as much Senſuality in practice, as of Hereticalneſs in judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Between the Play-houſes, and the Coffee-houſes, the Tavern, and other places of ſenſual delights, peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:61171:30"/>loſe that time which can never be regained. Some are noted to make the time of their Mornings-draughts to laſt from ſeven or eight, to one or two in the After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noon; that add (as one ſpeaks) feathers to the wings of <hi>Time,</hi> and make it a ſtudy to ſend that going, which they cannot hinder from going. Though it be poſſible, not to loſe time; yet 'tis impoſſible to hold and detain it, <hi>Potes non perdere, non potes tenere.</hi> The Prodigals of time ſhould ſet this frugal improver of it before them, when they are prone to this fooliſh expenſiveneſs.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Great and admirable was his <hi>prudence</hi> in his Speech and Behaviour; He was one that knew to whom he ſpake, when to ſpeak, and how much to ſpeak; one that knew how to benefit others, and yet not to inſnare himſelf by ſpeaking. Though I know that <hi>pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctical Prudence</hi> to guide us in the courſe of our life, be a different gift from, and perhaps not often joyned with ſpeculative and intellectual knowledg (it being grown to a Proverb, that <hi>the greateſt Scholars are not always the wiſeſt men</hi>); yet <hi>both</hi> theſe Ornaments did eminently meet in this our Doctor; His wiſdom made not only his own face to ſhine, but by example and counſel he reflected much of the luſtre of it upon others. And I much queſtion whether any perſon in <hi>London</hi> (Miniſter or private Chriſtian) was more fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently deſired to give advice and counſel in affairs of difficulty, than was Doctor <hi>Seaman.</hi> His pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dential reſervedneſs, was indeed by ſome accounted exceſſive ſeverity and moroſity (the more was I engaged to him for his free and frequent diſcourſes with me). And yet notwithſtanding this natural, if we may call it ſeverity; ſometimes he knew how to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:61171:31"/>be very chearful, though in a grave and in a Chriſtian way. The laſt time he was at my Houſe (where pardon great affection in making a ſmall digreſſion) he was received by a now bleſſed Saint, with great joy and thankfulneſs, who yet more rejoyced to ſit at this feet, than to have him ſit at her Table, and is now nearer to him, than ſhe is to my ſelf.) At that time (I ſay) he was pleas'd to allow himſelf that innocent chearfulneſs and freeneſs of Carriage and Expreſſion, as ſhewed us only how well it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came him then to do ſo: And theſe would have been expreſſed by him oftner, had he not been hindered either by ſtudy or conſtitution.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Laſtly, I ſhall view him in his deportment in his laſt <hi>great affliction</hi> by that Pain and Sickneſs, of which he dyed. His Patience in the time of his Sickneſs was great even to admiration and aſtoniſhment; when Pains ſtrove for victory, Patience clearly won it; in all his torments he ſeldom groaned under them, but he never grumbled againſt him that ſent them. This our <hi>Lazarus</hi> laid open his ſores before God, and often complained <hi>to</hi> him; yet he never com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained <hi>of</hi> him. In the midſt of his tortures, he admired free Grace, Juſtification by Faith, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanced that God that ſeemed ſo much to depreſs him; conſidering his natural temper, his patience and his ſubmiſſion to God in his Afflictions, were incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable and imitable. I never admired his Scholarſhip ſo much as I did his Patience, the Leſſon in which he grew ſo perfect in the School of Affliction: His Preaching and Patience put me in mind of what St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſpeaks concerning Chriſt, <hi>When he Preached, he Preached as a Shepherd, but when he was ſilent, he
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:61171:31"/>was ſilent as a Sheep.</hi> Sive docebat, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He that ſpake here in this Pulpit as your Shepherd, was as ſilent as a ſheep, when in his Chamber he lay under his Affliction; he never made any ſigns of diſcontent. When God took away the uſe of his Tongue, his ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence was not more from impotency of ſpeaking, than from the Grace of ſubmiſſion; he puts me in mind of that Martyr, who going to the fire, ſaid, <hi>Lord I will ſtoop, and thou ſhalt ſtrike; I will bow, and thou ſhalt beat, ſince my Soul is ſaved from eternal heats.</hi> I conclude from all I have ſaid of him:</p>
            <p>Firſt, Let all lament this publick loſs; <hi>England</hi> lament the loſs of ſo great an Inſtrument of Gods glory; <hi>Cambridge</hi> lament your loſs of ſo great a Scholar; <hi>London</hi> lament your loſs of ſo great a Divine; you his People lament the loſs of ſo faithful a Paſtor: I am ſure his Family muſt lament the loſs of ſuch a Father and Maſter; and without hypocriſie, I put my ſelf into the number of theſe Mourners, who have parted with ſo dear and faithful a friend. Let us all mourn, and know and ſay, That a great man, a Prince in Learning and excellent Parts, is faln (do you not know it?) in this our <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Imitate him in his Graces; (in his gifts I do not expect it, I know you cannot) eſpecially imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate him in his great Patience; and remember that counſel of the Apoſtle, <hi>James</hi> 5.10. which I ſhall give you but with a ſmall variation, <hi>Take, my brethren, this Prophet who hath ſpoken in the name of the Lord, for an example of ſuffering affliction, and of patience.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, Remember his heavenly Doctrines, and feed and live upon them. The Flowers of Learned Authors which he fed upon in his Studies, he gave
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:61171:32"/>you not in kind; thoſe I deſire you not therefore to take from him; but the nouriſhing milk he gave you of Holy Doctrine, into which he turned thoſe flowers taken from his Authors; take it in, and retain it for your ſpiritual nouriſhment; and remember he did not only give you the Texts of his Sermons, but the large Comment, and the Exemplification of them in an heavenly imitable converſation.</p>
            <p>Fourthly and laſtly, This is all I will ſay, ('Tis in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference unto <hi>Succeſſion</hi>) If you know of any that he did commend to you for a Succeſſor, let him be emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently in your thoughts for your acceptation; or if you know of any that you are confident he would have approved of, had he known him; let your ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation be agreeable to what you judg by his judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and practice would have been his.</p>
            <p>I ſay no more, but the Lord grant when you come to conſider of that affair, you may be <hi>unani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous,</hi> and that you may have no contention, but who ſhall ſhew moſt love to Chriſt, to Souls, to one another, and to the memory of your late worthy Paſtor.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAg. 5. l. 5. read <hi>ſuppling,</hi> p. 7. l. 5. dele <hi>ſaith the Apoſtle,</hi> p. 7. l. 14. r.
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 12. l. 14. r. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, p. 16. l. 13. r. <hi>profana,</hi> p. 43. l. 6. r. <hi>ſtudium.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
